Contact

5133724114 (Mobile) koonerts@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/koonerts (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Groovy MySQL Hive/Spark

Certifications

Certified Neo4j Professional

Taranjit Kooner

Senior Software Engineer | FinTech & Distributed Data Processing | Ex-Meta

Seattle, Washington, United States

Summary

Senior engineer with expertise in large-scale distributed payment systems and financial infrastructure, previously at Meta. Architected reconciliation systems handling complex payment flows across many global payment providers. Recognized for technical excellence in system design, performance optimization, and infrastructure/codebase modernization.

Experience

Meta

3 years 7 months

Sr. Partner Engineer - Meta FinTech (MFT) July 2022 - December 2024 (2 years 6 months) Seattle, Washington, United States

- Built/architected File Management System (FMS), a platformized framework for importing/exporting/processing payment related files, processing 10s of millions of daily transactions across 250+ settlement files across 12+ global/ regional payment providers; Reduced new provider/use-case onboarding from 6–12 weeks to 2–4 weeks
- Migrated/rewrote significant pieces of MFT Recon+Alerting Python codebases to utilize concurrent/async IO + parallel processing; improved settlement file processing for large providers by 25x–35x (6+ hrs → 10–15 mins); Reduced overall daily parallel processing time for all settlements from 10+ hrs to 30–40 mins, ultimately helping Treasury/Finance XFN to close month-end books consistently by day 2
- Identified/fixed inefficiencies in critical company-wide CLI tooling (Meta's blob storage service), improving unordered file search/traversal performance by 65%–95% from ~5min–10hrs+ to a consistent ~3–5 secs (dependent on search/bucket characteristics)

- Implemented Apple IAP (In-App Purchase) reconciliation for FB/Instagram Ads Boost in US, protecting over \$1B in revenue while maintaining compliance with Apple App Store requirements.
- Provided technical leadership and mentorship to junior engineers on reconciliation systems, FMS implementation, and payment processing best practices.

Partner Engineer - Meta FinTech (MFT) June 2021 - June 2022 (1 year 1 month) Seattle, Washington, United States

- Led migration of 185k+ merchants/shops to PayPal's v3 APIs for Facebook/ Instagram Shops, coordinating with 8+ cross-functional teams to ensure compliance with FINCen and Tax/IRS requirements.
- Designed, built, and launched Partner Self-Certification Portal (PSCP), enabling LATAM payment partners to independently test their Meta Pay API implementation, significantly reducing partner engineering overhead and accelerating onboarding.

bswift

5 years 9 months

Sr. Software Engineer II December 2020 - May 2021 (6 months)

Chicago, Illinois, United States

- Led the solutioning and re-architecture of a in-house data comparison/ migration tool.
- Led the solutioning of a project to improve the performance of bSwift's most highly utilized partner API connection.
- Conducted several large code refactors to clean up technical debt, ultimately leading to a 50% improvement in latency + 70% cost reduction for bSwift's AWS APIGateway usage.

Sr. Software Engineer I
January 2019 - December 2020 (2 years)
Chicago, Illinois, United States

• Implemented bswift's first project(s) utilizing cloud infrastructure; A general purpose customer service chatbot utilizing AWS Lex and AI assisted document search utilizing AWS Kendra.

- Implemented a deployment pipeline using the AWS CDK/Lambda/CodeBuild/ CodePipeline/S3/etc to facilitate Continuous Integration and Deployment (CICD) for AWS related resources/projects. AWS resources were described using Infrastructure as Code (IaC) principles using the AWS CDK library.
- Implemented bswift's first project utilizing graph databases (Neo4j), which facilitates data integrity in the process of data migration between a source and target environment.
- Implemented bswift's first fully asynchronous API + event-queue processor to replace the demographic flat-file import for one of bswift's largest clients, handling several million events per month.

Software Engineer

June 2017 - January 2019 (1 year 8 months)

Chicago, Illinois, United States

- Refactored a large portion of the bswift database and codebase in a yearlong project spanning 2000+ files, to better handle persisting environment specific configuration after database refreshes from Prod to 9+ lower environments.
- Improved the processing performance of bswift's most used flat file import (demographic data) by 300%.
- Created 30+ web pages to house both default and client connection (API/ SSO) configuration.
- Handled delegating work to contractors along with handling code reviews.
- Maintained/improved 20+partner API/SSO connections.
- Mentored/Taught junior developers about various areas of the bswift system.

Junior Software Engineer

September 2015 - June 2017 (1 year 10 months)

Chicago, Illinois, United States

 Quickly switched and adapted to working on many integral parts of the bswift codebase, ranging from Imports, Exports/EDI, Payroll, and API/SSO data connections.

- Improved the processing time of bswift's largest client's export file processing by 5300%, from 9hrs to 10 mins.
- Developed and integrated one of the first embed API connections in bSwift, allowing customers to interact with partner sites/resources during enrollment flow without leaving the bSwift site.

Education

Miami University

Bachelor of Science - BS, Computer Engineering · (2011 - 2015)